<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Middleborovv. A briefe rehersall of the accorde and agreement, that the captaynes, burgises, and armie of Middleborovv and Armevv: have made, in yelding the[m]selves to the right high and excellent prince, the Lorde William Prince of Orrange, Countie of Nassau, &amp;c. With a lamentable discourse of the calamities, great hungre [and] extreame miseries, that they sustayned, before they yelded by the sayd townes. Translated out of the ducthe coppy, printed at Dordrecht. Anno 1574.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1574</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100905</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836732</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836732</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1018</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07481)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1018)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1320:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Middleborovv. A briefe rehersall of the accorde and agreement, that the captaynes, burgises, and armie of Middleborovv and Armevv: have made, in yelding the[m]selves to the right high and excellent prince, the Lorde William Prince of Orrange, Countie of Nassau, &amp;c. With a lamentable discourse of the calamities, great hungre [and] extreame miseries, that they sustayned, before they yelded by the sayd townes. Translated out of the ducthe coppy, printed at Dordrecht. Anno 1574.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richarde Jhones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1574]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: tr. Aprilis.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Dutch original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 17865a on UMI microfilm reel 1320.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1018:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:1018:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->
            <p>
               <hi>MIDDLEBOROVV.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A briefe Reherſall of the accorde and agreement, that the Captaynes, Burgiſes, and Armie of <hi>MIDDLEBOROVV</hi> and <hi>ARMEVV:</hi> haue made, in yelding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the right high and excellent Prince, the Lorde William Prince of <hi>Orrange,</hi> Countie of <hi>Naſſau. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶With a lamentable Diſcourſe of the calamities, great hungre &amp; extreame miſeries, that they ſuſtayned, before they yelded vp the ſaid Townes.</p>
            <p>*<hi>Tranſlated out of the ducthe Coppy, printed at Dordrecht.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANNO <hi>1574.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶Imprinted at London, by Richarde Ihones.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="copy_of_accord">
            <pb facs="tcp:1018:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:1018:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->
            <head>The Coppy of the agreement and accord, betweene the Prince of Orange, &amp; them of Middelborrow and Armew as foloweth &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much as Sir Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Montdragon Knight, Lorde of Rembicourt, Captayne generall of the Wallowne Souldiers; being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante in the townes of Myddelbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row &amp; Armew: vpon requeſt made vnto him by the Captayne of Strenchamps, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng agayne out of Priſon) by his Letters dated the xvi. day of the ſame preſent Mourne, vnto the right highe &amp; excellent Prince, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde William prince of Orrange county of Naſſau &amp;c. Beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Maieſtie to ſend his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners vnto the Caſtell of Rammekens (named Seborrow) to <hi>parle</hi> with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, concerning the yeeldynge vp of the afore named Townes and Cities.</p>
            <p>¶ To the whiche requeſte his Maieſtye wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly graunted: and ſent his Commiſſioners to propoſe certayne Articles and Conditions to the Commiſſioners of the Lorde Mondragon, by the which meanes, their aforſayd offer to yeeld vp the Townes might be accepted. In conſideration whereof, the Commiſſioners mett together at the tyme appoynted, where betweene them the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and Articles aforeſayd were fully conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and agréeed vpon on both ſides, in maner and fourme followyng. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1018:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->FIrſt, the Lord of Montdragon, ſhal yelde and geue ouer the townes of Middel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borrow and Armew, without ſpoylynge of any Forte or demyniſhinge any ſtrengthe thereof preſently. And alſo al the Ordinance and muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Warres, with all ſuch Ships, Goodes and Marchandies as are therin. Yea, and he with al his Soldiers (ſuch as wyl not ſweare vnto his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency) ſhal immediatly avoyd out of the Iland of Walcheren, takeyng with them their wepons and Enſignes, with bagge &amp; bagadge to them be longing, ſimply and faithfully: not medlyng with any other Goods or parcelles, what ſoeuer to them not belongynge. And who that ſhall tranſgreſſe the ſaide Ordynaunce, carrynge away more then his owne, ſhall ſtande to the puniſhment of the ſaide Prince.</p>
            <p>¶ Moreouer, if that the Lorde Montdragon do not deliuer in ſafetie, within the ſpace of two Monethes into Hollande or Sealande, or ſome other place, vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuriſdic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Prince, theſe perſons hereafter named: That is to ſay: Phillip of Mariner Eſquier, the Lord of Mownte S. Aidegonde, the Captaine Iacob Simoiſſen, a Captaine that was taken in the <hi>HAGHE</hi> whoſe ſurname is Citadelle, the Liutenant of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, William of Angeren, and one more, whoſe ſurname is Pe in: then ſhall remaine in priſon, three Captaynes, three Liutennauntes, three En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne bearers, three Seriants of the Band: &amp; three
<pb facs="tcp:1018:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->
Corporals, accordyng to the law of Armes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll ſuch time as the Perſons aforeſayde be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered.</p>
            <p>¶ Likewiſe it ſhall be lawfull to departe oute of the ſayde Towne, all Victellers, Gonners, Commiſſioners, Shippers: <hi>Ian Coppes, Iaques Pardeuille,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their Seruants, writings, Letters Bagge and bagage, what ſo euer it bee, as alſo the Prieſtes and Monks, and men of Religion, onely with their habites (yf they wyll.)</p>
            <p>¶And his Maieſtie ſhall ſet ſuch good order in the premiſſes, that all thoſe which departe oute of the Iland with their goodes, as is before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, ſhal be ſhipped ouer into the Coaſts of Flaunders in good ſafetye, promiſinge the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Commiſſioners and Deputyes, by their faith and hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to ſtabliſh and perfourme in ful and ample maner, this aforeſayde agréement of the Prince of Orange, and the Lord Montdra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, reſpectiuely: &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more aſſurance wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Pledges on both ſides ſhalbe deliuered.</p>
            <p>¶ Theſe foreſayd Articles being agréed and concluded in the Fortreſſe of Rammekens, the xix. day of February. <hi>ANNO 1574.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beneath were written the one after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other: <hi>Duttem, Gillis de villain, Anthoni de Gerardt, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coys de Bouchant, Iunius de longe, Arendt van Dorpe, Charles de Boiſot.</hi> And a litle lower was written, We <hi>VVilliam</hi> of <hi>Naſſou,</hi> on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one ſide: &amp; I <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pher
<pb facs="tcp:1018:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->
Montdragon</hi> Knight, Lorde of <hi>Rembycourte,</hi> of <hi>Lus, Guſſanuille</hi> on the other ſide: haue ſeene and peruſed the aforenamed agreement and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde: which with our wyls and ful conſent is concluded. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confirmation wherof we haue promiſed, &amp; by theſe preſents doo promiſe by our princely wordes and Honors, to performe and accompliſh, and cauſe to be perfourmed and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complyſhed, the whole conſents of the ſame in al poynts and Articles, without gaynſaying, or ſuffer to be gaynſayde, them, or any parte of them.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>In witneſſe wherof we haue ſubſcribed and Sealed to the ſame, <date>the foreſayde .xix. day of February in the yeare aforeſayde.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>And beneath was ſubſcribed.
<list>
                     <item>Guillam de Naſſou.</item>
                     <item>Chriſtopher de Montdragon.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="copy_of_proclamation">
            <head>The coppy of the Proclamation, ſet foorth by the Prince of Orrange.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E William, by the grace of God, Prince of Orrang, County of Naſſou &amp;c. Gouernour of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Seela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Freeſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; Vtreght: vnderſtandynge that the Burge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters of the Towne of Middel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borrow,
<pb facs="tcp:1018:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->
haue ſimply declared &amp; moſte humbly haue cauſed to be ſhewed vnto vs, in the name of them ſelues, their Cittezins, &amp; the Coronel Montdragon: their extreame muertes, hunger and calamities: haue therfore of meere compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, earneſtly mouinge vs to embrace Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an mercy, aboue rigor and crueltye, thought it good to declare vnto them by theſe preſents theſe Articles followyng.</p>
            <p>¶ Firſt, the aforeſayd Cittezns, ſuch as wyl ſweare to vs on the behalfe of the Kings Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, ſhalbe vnder our obeyſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in his Maieſties behalfe as other Cities and Townes: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſaue and retayne their bodies &amp; goods with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reproche, or rehearſall of any matters that ar paſt. For the aſſurance wherof, we ſhal cauſe a certaine nomber of our Burgiſes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> townes of <hi>Sieri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zee Vliſſyng:</hi> and <hi>Camphere</hi> to be placed in the ſame to keepe out our Souldiers &amp; Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Intendyng alſo by all meanes poſſible to ſuppreſſe &amp; quench the hatred of other townes conceiued againſt them.</p>
            <p>¶ And who ſo euer is not diſpoſed to be ſworne as afore is ſayde, we wyll chuſe of them ten men, which we ſhal keepe in the ile of Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheren, to the end they ſhall cauſe to be dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered (by what means ſo euer it be) the Burge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter with other Cittezins of Harlam in lyke nomber.</p>
            <p>¶The other good Cittizins that are there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb facs="tcp:1018:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->
or heareafter ſhall come, ſhall hencefoorth occupy their trade of Marchandies: and vſe and enioy their rightes &amp; Priuelidges within theyr limmits, as they haue bin accuſtomed in times paſt, we (only) retayning to our ſelues the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to make prouiſion for them of Camphere, Vliſſynge, and Armew, with other ſuch lyke places, for al ſuch neceſſaryes as we ſhal ſe good and expedient.</p>
            <p>¶ Wee doo you to vnderſtande alſo, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng the propoſition of thrée hundreth thouſand Gildens, being demaunded of vs: the Cittizens ſhall pay by generall conſent, ſuch a reaſonable ſome of Mony to the mayntinance of the Army, and helpyng to driue away the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of our natiue Land, and Country, according as we ſhall finde it meete to ceaſe them after their abillytie, not comprehendinge heerein the Vplandyſh men which haue ſuſtayned and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed our aduerſaryes, concerninge whom wee wyll heere after conſider off, and ſet order for them.</p>
            <p>¶ More ouer the Cittizens ſhalbe bownde to take dillygent heede that none of the Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, or ſpirituall Goodes, or any other thinge be conuayed priuely, digged, or caryed away: but ſhall foorthwith, preſ nt al ſuch goods &amp; Iuelles as they ſhal know to be buried, conuated away or geuen to any Body to keepe, or otherwiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gyng to ſpyritual, or other perſons, that keep
<pb facs="tcp:1018:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->
themſelues without the Ilande of Walcheren: and that vpon paine of bodily puniſhment.</p>
            <p>¶ Further, concernynge the requeſt of the Burgemaſters aforeſaid: (namely) that the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizins, that ar fled before this time, might now come again to their goodes and poſſeſſions: wée ſhall hereafter conſider therof, and diſpoſe the ſame, as ſhalbe méete and conuenient in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>And alſo, touching the foreſaid requeſt of the Burgemaiſters, and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners of Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borrow: concerning prieſtes, ſpiritual perſons, deuine ſeruice, Churchegoods: and debtes, made by occaſſion of this warre: with other poinctes giuen vp by them in writyng: the Prieſtes and ſpirituall perſones, ſhall departe with their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bittes vpon them: the reſt, we ſhall diſpoſe at tyme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient, for the moſte profit of the Citie and countrey, in ſuch reaſonable order, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhalbe thought méete.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>*<hi>Geuen, in the Towne of Vlisſing, vnder our hande and Seale:</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> .xix. <hi>daye of Februarie. Anno.</hi> 1574.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account_of_siege">
            <pb facs="tcp:1018:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <head>¶Hereafter foloweth a ſhort reherſall of the calamities, great hunger and extreme myſeries, that they ſuſtayned in Middlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and Armew, before they yelded vp the ſaide Townes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen thei of <hi>Middleborow</hi> and <hi>Armew,</hi> ſaw that there was no more ayde: and that all their prouiſion, (aſwell fuell, as meat and drinke) was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed: And that their hunger- (whiche is a ſharpe Sworde) encrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed more &amp; more: they imagyned, how to ſaue their wiues &amp; children: which they could not do, becauſe thei had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted mo Souldiers, then they were able to gouerne.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, (that is to be lamented) the Coronel &amp; his Souldiers, by great violence, haue taken out of the poore Citezins Houſes, all kind of vittailes wherwith they might haue ſuſtayned the liues of their wyues and children,
<pb facs="tcp:1018:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
beatyng them, &amp; handlyng them moſte rigorouſly: yea, takyng the bread and vittayles, euen oute of the Childrens mouthes: and carried al the prouiſion of vittaylles, into their Campes and Trenches: not regarding the pittyful lamentations and complaints of the Cittezins. By theſe meanes, were the Citezins conſtrayned (with their wiues and children,) to ſuffer a moſte miſerable hungre, the ſpace of ſeuen weekes longe: ſo that they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to buy for their meate, Rattes, Cattes, Mice and Dogges: with the fleſſhe of other Beaſtes, that are not meete for man to eate, and to pay for the ſame full dearelye. For a pounde of Horſe fleſſhe, was ſoulde for .xii.d. a quarter of a Dog, was ſoulde for two ſhyllynges .iiii.<abbr>d.</abbr> a Rat .viii.<abbr>d.</abbr> and a Mowce .ii.<abbr>d.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>When this kinde of ſuſtenance was conſumed and eaten: and that there was no more bread lefte: there weare
<pb facs="tcp:1018:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
fownde within the Townes certayne Garners, wherin was Hempſeed, and Lynſeede, wherof the Citizins made them dread: And for aſmuche, as they coulde not eate it after it was bakte: they did knead it agayne with water, and bakte it (as Wafers) in an Iron.</p>
            <p>But (alas,) by meanes therof, the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizins be ſo rotted and ſpoiled in their gutts, that it is greatly to be doubted of their lyues and healthes.</p>
            <p>And when I call to minde, how that (aſwell) the Elders, as others, muſt ſhut vp their children fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and fellow Citezins, I can not refraine me from weeping: As for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: a woman of good credit, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from Midleborrow, did moſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifullye complayne, that ſhe was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſhutte vp her children three weekes long, leaſt they were taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her to be killed and eaten. But all this whyle, the Coronel and his Soul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diers liued of the breade and vittaylle
<pb facs="tcp:1018:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
that they had taken ſo longe ago, tyll they weare come to halfe a pounde of bread a day: after that to a quarter of a li. and at the laſte, to halfe a quarter of a pownd. And finally, the Soldiers (for all their daintineſſe,) haue beene conſtrayned to eate with the Citizins the oyllie Cakes. And the fat bellyed and wel fed Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes in the rich Abbey, died for hunger. Wherby may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, what great myſerie and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Cittezins, with their wiues and children, moſte lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tably haue ſuſtained.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note_to_the_reader">
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Reader.</head>
            <p>WE mean not here (good reader) to hide from thée: how fayre and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey of Walcheren is: how profitable to all Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treies neare by, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, neither Holland, Sealand, Brabande, and Flaunders: yea, the whole Nauigation
<pb facs="tcp:1018:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
in no wiſe (can be maintayned.</p>
            <p>And for aſmuche: as, the poore chaſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, haue now (the ſpace of ſeuen yeares) ben driuen, from one Countrey to an other, &amp; haue ben greatly tormented vnder the Croſſe: not knowynge wheare they might haue a reſtynge place. Our God therfore, of his mercifull goodneſſe, (as it is euident to euery mans ſight) hath ordayned this lande of Walcheren, as a ſure lodgyng and refuge, wherin the may main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne themſelues in the time of this Pilgre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. And thus, beſéechyng your goodneſſes, that we may all together giue hartie thankes to God: and to attribute this victorie all onely vnto him, not doubtyng, but he will ſo proſéede with the other countreys that are yet vnder the Tirrannie of the ennemie: and ſo gratiouſly delyuer them: to the magnifieng of his holy name, and the ſaluation of their ſoules. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>☞ THE CONCLVSION.</head>
            <p>FOr the accompliſſhement of that poinct afore rehearſed, makynge mencion of the Lorde St. Aldegonde and the other priſoners. The Coronell Montdragon, hath geuen his Letters of Obligation, that he ſhall delyuer
<pb facs="tcp:1018:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
them, and ſet them at libertie, within two Monethes, eyther in Hollande, Sealande, or any other place, that is vnder his Maieſties iuriſdiction.</p>
            <p>For defaute wherof, on his behalfe: the ſaide Coronell, ſhall yelde himſelfe perſonally, within the foreſaid ſpace, into the handes of his excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie.</p>
            <trailer>¶ FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>ix. APRILIS.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
